Finding Aid for Arc Michigan records, 1956-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arc Michigan records 1956-2007, 1980-2004
Arc Michigan.
1 motion picture reel
7.5 linear feet
9965 Aa 2
Advocacy organization established to protect the rights of developmentally challenged individuals; records include meeting minutes, reports and publications, affiliate files, and visual materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group was donated by The Arc Michigan (donor no. 8857 ) beginning in 1999; additions were received in 2009.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Arc Michigan is an association dedicated to positively affect the lives of people with disabilities and their families through advocacy, education and monitoring. It is directly affiliated with The Arc, a national association, which was founded in the 1950's by a group of parents whose children needed special assistance.
In 1953 the name was changed to "Michigan Association for Retarded Children" and in 1982, after numerous name changes their current name was selected.
During the early days, The Arc concentrated on public education and advocacy and individual and family support. By 1989, there were a total of 62 local units and about 6300 member families advocating for the rights of the disabled and mentally retarded.
The Arc Michigan conducts yearly strategic planning to update its goals and to stay current with the evolving needs of people with disabilities. This plan is what determines future activities, budgets, programs, staff and volunteer recruitment to provide services such as civil rights, health care and early intervention and education.
The records of The ARC date primarily from the 1980's until 2007, with some documents from the 1950's through the 1970's. They include meeting minutes, surveys, grant proposals, project documentation, correspondence and publications. These records document the various projects of this organization, including advocacy and individual care. The records are arranged into eight series as follows: Board and Governance, Committees, Conferences and Collaborations, Reports and Programs, Publications, Affiliates, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Arc Michigan.; Children with disabilities--Michigan.; Developmental disabilities--Michigan.; Mental retardation--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Arc Michigan.; Handicapped persons--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Board and Governance
  The Board and Governance series includes history, mission, manuals, by laws, policies, and strategic plans, meeting minutes, grants, member biographies, position statements, resolutions and some correspondence.
  - History and milestones (Box 1)
  - Mission and vision statements 1998-1999, undated (Box 1)
  - President's manual 1991 (Box 1)
  - Director's manual 1991 (Box 1)
  - By laws
    - 1985-1996 (Box 1)
    - 2000, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Policies and procedures 1983-1994 (Box 1)
  - Planning
    - Strategic planning committee minutes 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - Strategic plan 1981-2004 (Box 1)
    - Development plan
      - 1981-1982 (Box 1)
      - 1993-1996 (Box 1)
    - Operational plan 1992-1994 (Box 1)
    - Position statements (Box 1)
    - Resolutions (Box 1)
    - Board retreat 1994 (Box 1)
  - Minutes
    - 1988-1995 (Box 1)
    - 1996-1999 (Box 1)
    - 3/1999-12/1999 (Box 1)
    - 2/2000-10/2000 (Box 1)
    - 1/2001-12/2001, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1/2002-12/2002, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1/2003-8/2003, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 8/2003-8/2004, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Grants and budget requests
    - Dated files
      - 1980-1986 (Box 2)
      - 1988-1992 (Box 2)
    - Reports
      - Agency review 1987-1997 (Box 2)
      - Capital Area 1991-1994 (Box 2)
      - Kalamazoo and South East Michigan 1994-1996 (Box 2)
      - Out come highlights reports
        - 1994-1995 (Box 2)
        - 1996-1997 (Box 2)
      - Allocations (United Way) 1993-1997 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - 1/1989-12/1991 (Box 2)
    - 1994-2003 (Box 2)
- Committees
  The Committees series consists of minutes of the various committees and their activities: Membership, Education, Executive, Nominating, Finance and Search.
  - Committee Goals and Objectives 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Executive committee
    - Biographies of Executive Committee and Directors at Large (Box 2)
    - Minutes
      - 1991-1995 (Box 2)
      - 3/1996-9/2000 (Box 2)
      - 9/2000-12/2003 (Box 3)
  - Audit / Finance
    - Audit committee 2/1990-12/2002 (Box 3)
    - Audits / Financial Statements
      - 1956-1969 1971-1993, 39 reports (in 1 expandable folder) (Box 3)
      - 2001, 2004 (Box 3)
    - Finance committee 1/1988-4/2004, 2 folders
      - Financial position 2002 (Box 3)
      - Budget
        - 1993 (Box 3)
        - 3/1994-11/1994, 1/1995 (Box 3)
  - Education committee
    - Minutes
      - 9/1981-9/1999 (Box 3)
      - 1998-2000, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 2001 (Box 4)
      - 1/2002-3/2005 (Box 4)
    - Special Education, quarterly progress reports 2002-2003 (Box 4)
    - Newspaper clippings 2002-2003 (Box 4)
  - Membership committee 1991-1996 (Box 4)
  - Nominating committee minutes
    - 1/1995-3/1999 (Box 4)
    - 4/1999-2/2002 (Box 4)
    - 4/2003-11/2003 (Box 4)
    - 2004 (Box 4)
  - Search committee 2003 (Box 4)
- Conferences and Collaborations
  The series on Conferences and Collaborations includes information concerning annual conferences as well as joint conferences and collaborative efforts with other organizations such as the Autism Society and Wayne State University. This series also includes minutes, brochures photographs and hand outs, evaluations and participant information.
  - Annual 1999 (Box 4)
  - Annual 2000 (joint conference with Autism society) (Box 4)
    (include photographs)
  - Annual 2001 (Box 4)
  - Annual 2003 (Box 4)
  - Annual 2004 (Box 4)
  - Annual 2006 (Box 4)
  - Other Conferences and Collaborations
    - Brochures and fliers (Box 4)
- Reports
  The Reports series provides information and evaluation of the various programs conducted by The ARC.
  - Annual 1989-2007 (Box 4)
  - End of Year 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Family Information Exchange County 1998-1999 (Box 4)
  - Family Information Exchange County 2002, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Family Information Exchange County 2003, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Resource Development Reports 2/1990-4/1996 (Box 5)
- Programs
  The Programs series includes information on the various programs such as Early On, Dignified Lifestyles, Parent Leadership Program and activities such as various family gatherings.
  - Early On
    - Early On Cultural competency committee 2003 (Box 5)
    - Early On Infant Toddler intervention system grant 2000, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Revised Early On individualized family service plan 1999-2005 (Box 5)
    - Data collection projects 1999-2000 (Box 5)
    - Newsletters 1998-2005 (Box 5)
  - Parent Leadership Program
    - Grant 1996-2005, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Minutes
      - 1997-1999 (Box 5)
      - 2000 (Box 5)
      - 2001 (Box 5)
    - Parent training Kit (Box 5)
  - Family support
    - Outreach grant 1998-2003, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Family Gatherings
    - 1999
      - Lapeer (Box 6)
      - Oakland (Box 6)
      - Traverse Bay Area (Box 6)
      - Kalamazoo (Box 6)
      - Oceana and Muskegon (Box 6)
      - Alpena (Box 6)
      - Escanaba/Schoolcraft (Box 6)
    - 2000 (Box 6)
    - Statistics and Analysis of Family Gatherings (Box 6)
  - Dignified Lifestyles minutes
    - 1991-1996 (Box 6)
    - 1997, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 1/1998-7/1998 (Box 6)
    - 8/1998-7/1999 (Box 6)
  - Residential Services Monitoring Program 1988-1990 (Box 6)
  - Activism and advocacy
    - Developmental Disabilities Council / Michigan Department of Mental Health (correspondence)
      - 6/1991-12/1993 (Box 6)
      - 1/1994-11/1994 (Box 6)
      - 1/1995-8/1995 (Box 6)
    - Group homes issues
      - Correspondence 1988 (Box 6)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 6)
  - Awards, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Publications
  The Publication series includes brochures, newsletters, fliers and other hand outs published and used by The Arc and its affiliates.
  - Newsletters 1992-2007 (Box 6)
  - Books 1957, 1962 (Box 6)
  - Brochures and fliers
    - West and South West region (Box 6)
    - Upper Peninsula region (Box 6)
  - Media Campaign and News release 1986-1996 (Box 6)
- Affiliates and Affiliated Organizations
  The Affiliates series includes information on the various local affiliates, by county, in Michigan, their activities and including fee issues and additional correspondence. This series is arranged in alphabetical order.
  - County ARC organizations
    - Allegan-Arenac (Box 7)
    - Bay-Copper Country (Box 7)
    - Dearborn-Down River (Box 7)
    - Genesee-Jackson (Box 7)
    - Kalamazoo-Livingston (Box 7)
    - Macomb-Muskegon (Box 7)
    - Newaygo-Ottawa (Box 7)
    - Plymouth-St.Clair (Box 7)
    - Tuscola-Western Wayne (Box 7)
  - Fee Issues -- ARC affiliates (Box 7)
  - Affiliations with United Way and Wayne State University
    - 1981-1985 (Box 7)
    - 12/91-3/94, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - 1994-1999 (Box 7)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series consists of photographs of some staff of The Arc and of various events and conferences. Also in this series are a number of video tapes some produced by The Arc and others acquired for use by staff. A number of motion pictures are also found in this series.
  - Photographs
    - Events (Box 7)
    - Staff (Box 7)
  - Videotapes (VHS copies)
    - "The Arc Michigan, Buddy Bell PSA" (Box 8)
    - "Advance Michigan, Vote NO, Proposals A and C 1992" (Box 8)
    - "The Ride, The Arc Cycling Program" (Box 8)
    - "Billy Hawkins with Dr. Mike Kneale 1990" (Box 8)
    - "Being an Effective Child Advocate" (Box 8)
    - "Parent Leadership Program at The Arc Michigan" (Box 8)
  - Motion Picture
    - "Something in Common" (Reel 1)